Guide to the Marjorie Tooker Whittlesey Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Marjorie Tooker Whittlesey Papers
1927-1991
RG 197
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(18 boxes)
Correspondence and writings document the life and work of Marjorie Tooker Whittlesey and her parents, and the operations of Yale-in-China during World War II. The collection also contains substantive documentation of the life and work of Ilma Ruth Aho, a Finnish missionary about whom Whittlesey wrote a biography.
Whittlesey, Marjorie T. (Marjorie Tooker), 1912-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jean Whittlesey, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Marjorie Tooker Whittlesey served as a registered nurse at the Yale-in-China hospital in Changsha, China from 1939 to 1944 and 1946-1947. Following her marriage and return to the United States she wrote numerous short stories, books, and articles. Her parents, Mary and Frederick J. Tooker M.D., were Presbyterian missionaries in Kuling, Kiangsi during her childhood and early adult life.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence and writings document the life and work of Marjorie Tooker Whittlesey and her parents, and the operations of Yale-in-China during World War II. The collection also contains substantive documentation of the life and work of Ilma Ruth Aho, a Finnish missionary about whom Whittlesey wrote a biography.
This collection is complementary to the Yale-China Association archives held at Yale's Sterling Memorial Library. Marjorie Tooker Whittlesey's letters, collected material, and autobiographical writings provide detailed documentation of her life and work as administrator of nursing at the Yale-China hospital in Changsha during the second World War. This collection also provides valuable insight into the dynamics of missionary family life, since Whittlesey's parents were Presbyterian missionaries. The parents, who had six children, were stationed in China prior to 1927, based in the U.S. 1927-1931, and then returned to Kuling.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1927-1963
II. General Correspondence, 1927-1983
III. Writings, 1934-1991
IV. Subject Files, 1944-1950
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1927-1988
Missionaries -- China -- Biography; Missions -- China; Nurses -- China; Women missionaries -- Biography; Missionaries; Aho, Ilma Ruth; Whittlesey, Marjorie T. (Marjorie Tooker), 1912-; Yale-in-China Association
- Family Correspondence, 1927-1963; Series I
  - Chronological sequence
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, 1924, 1927 Jan-1930 Feb (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, incl. re. conditions in Kuling (4/9/30), 1930 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, incl. re. conditions in China (5/28, 7/11, 7/13), 1930 May-Jul (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, incl. re. conditions in China (10/15, 10/29, 11/6), 1930 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, 1931 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents returned to China 1931 Jul, 1931 Jun-Aug (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling, 1931 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Shanghai, 1932 Jan (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling, 1932 Feb-May (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling, incl. re. Chiang Kai Shek, 1932 Jun (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling, 1932 Jul-1933 Dec (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling; Marjorie in China, 1934 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling; Marjorie in China; parents in Kuling; Marjorie in China, 1935 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents return to U.S., 1935 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, 1935 Jun-Dec (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, 1936 Jan-Jul (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; mother in U.S., father in Kuling, 1936 Aug-Dec (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; parents in Kuling, 1937 Jan-Dec (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; mother in Shanghai, 1938 Jan-Dec (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - To Marjorie from sister Dorothy, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - From Marjorie in Yali, Changsha, 1942-43 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, 1944 Jan-Dec (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie at Camp Swift, Texas, 1945 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings, 1945 May-Jul (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie in Philippines, 1945 Aug-Sep (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie in Philippines; incl. re. death of John Birch, 1945 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie returned to U.S., 1946 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie, father returned to China, 1946 Jul-Oct (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie in Changsha, 1946 Nov-1947 Feb (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Letters to/from parents and siblings; Marjorie in Changsha; incl. re. engagement and marriage to Stephen Whittlesey, 1947 Mar-May (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Letters to/from parents, mother-in-law and siblings; Marjorie and Stephen in Changsha, 1947 Jun-Sep (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Letters to/from parents, mother-in-law, and siblings; Marjorie and Stephen returned to U.S., 1947 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Letters to/from parents, in-laws, cousins and siblings, 1948 Jan (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Letters to/from parents, in-laws, and siblings; incl. re. birth of child, 1948 Feb (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters to/from parents, in-laws, and siblings, 1948 Mar-1949 Dec (Box 4, Folder 3-12)
    - Letters to/from parents, in-laws, and siblings, 1950 Jan-Aug (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Letters to/from extended family, 1950 Sep-1953 Dec (Box 5, Folder 5-14)
    - Letters to/from extended family, 1954 Jan-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Undated/fragmentary letters
    - To/from family, no date (Box 6, Folder 5-15)
- General Correspondence, 1927-1983; Series II
  - Correspondence of Marjorie with John Birch and his mother, 1945-1946 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Incl. to Marjorie from Rachel Dowd, Arthur Rinden, Frances Schlosser of Yale-in-China, 1946 Jan - Jun (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Incl. from Rachel Dowd, Kenneth Scott Latourette, Kenneth Morland of Yale-in-China, 1946 Jul-Aug (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Incl. to Ken, Peter; from Frances Schlosser, Kenneth Morland of Yale-in-China, 1946 Sep - 1947 Mar (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Incl. to/from Kenneth Morland, Kenneth Scott Latourette, Dwight Rugh, Frances Schlosser of Yale-in-China, Dima (Dimitri) Afonsky, 1947 Apr-Oct (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Incl. from Rachel Dowd, Frances Schlosser, Dwight and Winifred Rugh of Yale-in-China, Dima Afonsky, 1947 Nov-1948 Feb (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Incl. from Kenneth Scott Latourette, Frances Schlosser Scherer, Newton Y.C. Liu, Dwight Rugh, Dima Afonsky, Mika Afonsky, Rachel Dowd. re. Yale-in-China, 1948 Mar-Oct (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Incl. from Dima Afonsky, Rachel Dowd, Frances Schlosser Scherer, Winifred Rugh, re. Yale-in-China; circular letter of George and Geraldine Fitch, 1948 Nov - 1949 Feb (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Incl. from Dima Afonsky, Dwight Rugh, Rachel Dowd, re. Yale-in-China, 1949 Apr-Dec (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Incl. from France Schlosser Scherer, Jenny Lind, Rachel Dowd, Dima Afonsky, re. Yale-in-China, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Incl. from Dima Afonsky, Mika Afonsky, Frances Schlosser Scherer, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Incl. from Dima Afonsky, Mika Afonsky, 1957-1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Incl. from Mika Afonsky, Ilmi, Cecelia and Albert Fitch, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Incl. from Cecelia Fitch, Institute of Children's Literature, 1962-1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of others: Letters of William Pettus, Yale-in-China doctor, and materials related to his death, 1944-1946 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1934-1991; Series III
  - Short Stories
    - Short Stories, quips, Reader's Digest, Ladies Home Journal, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Admiral to the Rescue; Another Refugee, no date (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Attraction of Opposites; By Faith and Thanksgiving; Catch a Falling Star, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Christmas Treat; Decisions, Decisions, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - A Dream Fulfilled (Thanksgiving), no date (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Escape from the Zoo; The Intruder; J. B. (John Birch), 1986 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Life in These United States; Living Color; A Gift of Pain, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - A Modern Hermit, no date (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Paradise Lost; The Perfect Courier; Prisoner of Hope, no date (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Red Flag of Courage; Serenity; So Little Faith, no date (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - With God's Help and Guts (with notes), 1953 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Travel Articles
    - Anguilla; China Tour; Grenada (with notes), no date (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Hostess Gift (Virgin Islands); Nevis; The New Grenada, no date (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - The Old and the New in St. Lucia; Peter Island Hotel (with notes), no date (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Oriental Gourmet (with notes);South Pacific Dream, no date (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - St. Lucia, Unpolished Gem of the Caribbean; What Price Holiday (Caribbean), no date (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Articles
    - Adult Daycare; Aspire Program; Happy Endings (with notes); Doug and Marty (missionary/Honduras); Refugees, no date (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Books - Manuscripts/Drafts/Notes
    - Autobiography of MTW
      - Published version: "The Dragon Will Survive" - published by Ashley Books, Inc, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Draft entitled "The Chinese Web": Preamble, Chapter 1; Chapter 2-3 manuscript, no date (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Draft entitled "The Chinese Web": Chapter 3 revisions, no date (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Draft entitled "The Chinese Web": Chapter 4 revision, no date (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Draft entitled "One Woman's War - An American Nurse in China during World War II", no date (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Children's book: "Growing Up Summer"
      - Published version "Growing Up Summer" - published by Acadia Press; Draft entitled "Ten Feet Tall", 1990 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Drafts entitled "Ten Feet Tall" and "Cormorants are Ugly", no date (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Biography of Ilma Ruth Aho
      - Published version: "Ilma Ruth Aho, A Worker in His Field: Faith and Courage of a Finnish Missonary" - published by Exposition Press of Florida, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Notes and Testimonies on I. R. Aho, no date (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Chapter 1-3 (three versions), no date (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Chapter 4-6 (manuscript), no date (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Chapters 7-9 (manuscript), no date (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Book in manuscript (A Worker in His Field), no date (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Aho correspondence: China )2/44, 12/44, 3/45); Japan (1/54, 1/55, 11/55, 12/55, 1/56, 4/56, 12/56, 2/57, 7/57, 1/58), 1944-1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Aho correspondence to Whittlesey re: book, 1981-1983 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Aho correspondence to others, 1970-1979 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Notes: Aho Life, no date (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Notes and correspondence: Aho Life, no date (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence about Aho Life, no date (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence re: Aho Book, no date (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Research for Aho Book, 1979-1982 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Notes, lists; research Aho book, no date (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Notes on Aho Thesis, no date (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence with Publishers - Aho Book, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence with Publishers - Aho Book, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Book review-Aho; Support for publication, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Finnish publications, correspondence, photos, no date (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence with publisher (Growing up Summer, Chinese Web), 1985 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous corres. with publishers
      - Writing Contests, Publisher list, no date (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence Exposition Press, 1984-1988 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence to Publishers, 1980-1988 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence from Publishers; Rejection Letters, 1980-1982 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Rejection letters, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Rejection letters (undated), no date (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence to Publishers, 1983-5 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Writings of Others
    - Masters thesis by Ilma Ruth Aho, "A Record of the Activities of the Finnish Missionary Society in Northwest Hunan, China, 1902-1952", pp.1-100, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 1-4)
    - Aho Sermon, Contract for translation, Robbery, Pittsburgh, R. Whelan, "The Flying Tigers", S. Noble, "The Arthur Chronicles"; Felicia (letter to Aho, Reader's Digest article, J. Whittlesey news article on Boston strike), 1953-1986 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - R. Hadden Announcement; E. Allen, "Educaton the Rescue"; misc. news articles, M. Tooker, Japan and Refugees in China War Zones"; Finnish Newspaper, 1935-1985 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Books and notes on China, 1934-1946 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Subject Files, 1944-1950; Series IV
  - Yale in China memos and accounts; Hsiang-Ya Hospital Report, "Nurses of China Fight On" - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China; Evacuation of Changsha, Trustees Meetings, 1944-1945 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Primarily Yale-in-China pamphlets and bulletins; list of furloughed Presbyterian missionaries, 1941-50 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1927-1988; Series V
  - Education: Wellesley College, Junior year abroad at University of Munich, Western Reserve University, 1928-1933 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Army Record; Lost Army Baggage, 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 4a, b)
  - Certificates, Diplomas for writing courses, Passport, 1983-1988 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Financial records, 1938-1982 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Tour/cruise correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - St. Lucia, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Shipboard information, pamphlets, notebooks, no date (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Concerts and Programs, 1927-1931 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Concerts and Programs, 1932-1955 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Wedding Invitations, Cards, no date (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous cards, no date (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Wedding cards/notes, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous notes, information, receipts, articles, no date (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Music, no date (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Photos (Family), no date (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Photos (non-family), no date (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Photos (miscellaneous), no date (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Negatives (China, school), no date (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Negatives (College, Germany), 1933 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Negatives (Miscellaneous), no date (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Diary - diary volume for 1920 but with entries for 1924 Jun - Aug (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Diaries, 1924, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Diaries, 1935-1938 (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - Notebooks 1980, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, Calendar, 1937, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - 1930 Passion Play at Oberammergau (Box 18, Folder 5)